A Guide to the Malcolm Wilson Papers FA075
Rockefeller Archive Center
Malcolm Wilson papers
1939-1979
Rockefeller Archive Center
Wilson, Malcolm
FA075
10 Cubic Feet 10 document cases
Biographical/Historical note
Malcolm Wilson was born on February 26, 1914, in New York, New York. He graduated from Fordham University in 1933 and from Fordham Law School in 1936. Wilson was first elected to the New York State Assembly in 1938 at the age of 24 and served for the next 20 years. In January of 1959, he was sworn in as Lieutenant Governor of New York. Following Governor Nelson Rockefeller's resignation in December 1973, Wilson served as Governor until January 1975. He then returned to his private law practice in White Plains, New York. Wilson died on March 13, 2000.
Scope and Contents note
This collection contains a portion of the personal papers of Malcolm Wilson, Lieutenant Governor of New York during Nelson A. Rockefeller's tenure as Governor of New York from 1959 to 1973. Wilson later became Governor upon Rockefeller's resignation in December 1973. These papers do not include materials from the period of Wilson's service as Governor (December 1973-January 1975), nor are there any materials pertaining to his unsuccessful 1974 campaign for Governor.
These files were maintained by Malcolm Wilson in his law offices in White Plains, New York. As Lieutenant Governor, Wilson often made official appearances on Rockefeller's behalf and thus spent a great deal of time speaking to local and state Republican organizations. He also spoke at many college and high school graduations, which is documented in the extensive speech material (Boxes 5-8). Of particular note in this collection are the files relating to what was called at the time the Capital City or South Mall Project and is now known as The Governor Nelson A. Rockefeller Empire State Plaza (Box 8) in Albany, New York. Also of interest are the extensive files on the planning of the 1964 New York World's Fair, for which Wilson served as Chairman of the New York State Commission on the World's Fair (Boxes 8 and 9).
During the 1958 gubernatorial campaign, Wilson accompanied Nelson Rockefeller throughout New York State to meet with all the county, city, and town Republican Chairs and Committees. Rather than use a Rockefeller limousine and chauffeur, Wilson insisted that they travel in his own Buick, and he shared the driving with Rockefellers' son Steven. Folder 23 documents that Wilson footed the bills on these "Travels with Rocky" and was reimbursed by the Westchester County Republican Committee.
Related Archival Materials note
Researchers may also want to look at other materials that relate to this collection that are found in the Rockefeller Family Collection. From Record Group 4, Nelson A. Rockefeller Personal, refer to Series J: Politics, and Series L: Projects. From Record Group 15, Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial, see Series 22: New York Office, Series 27: Public Relations, Series 33: Speeches, and Series 38: New York State Republican Fundraising Reports.
Additionally, researchers may wish to consult the Malcolm Wilson Papers, which are located at Fordham University in Bronx, New York.
File Plan note
Former Classification: IV 3A 27
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
This series was donated to the Rockefeller Archive Center in 2000.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for scholarly research except where particular restrictions are noted.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
New York (N.Y.); New York (State); Empire State Plaza (Albany, N.Y.); Albany (N.Y.); New York World’s Fair (1964-1965); Wilson, Malcolm; Republican Party (N.Y.). State Committee
- Nelson A. Rockefeller File, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  News clippings, editorials on death of NAR; United Nations memorial service on February 2, 1979; Malcolm Wilson memorial tribute to NAR in February 1979 Empire State Report; correspondence on NAR death; invitation to memorial service and reception; transcript of news conference on WABC TV Channel 7, January 29, 1979, Malcolm Wilson as guest.
- Malcolm Wilson Legislative Record, 1939-1958 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Two volumes compiled by Wilson staff: Legislation introduced by Wilson in the Assembly.
- Malcolm Wilson Letter Book, 1958-1974 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Personal letters from NAR to Malcolm Wilson; January 2, 1974 handwritten letter to Wilson from NAR; Wilson's response to President Ford's request to all U.S. Governors for suggestions of three names for U.S. Vice President.
- Malcolm Wilson Letter Book, 1967, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Photo of Wilson with Archbishop Spellman and Arthur Goldberg at Al Smith Dinner, October 17, 1967; Wilson speech at Al Smith Dinner; copies of letters on Wilson's speech from Archbishop Spellman, Mrs. John A. Warner, Thomas E. Dewey.
- Arthur J. Goldberg, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Book by Victor Lasky, "Arthur J. Goldberg: The Old and the New."
- Gubernatorial Campaign, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Campaign literature; news clippings; Ethics Commission Report (December 12, 1969); correspondence; legislature campaign material and correspondence; financial folder; campaign material; press releases; campaign financial statements.
- Campaign Finances, Gubernatorial, 1958, 1962, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  1958 filing statement; 1962 filing statement, plane and hotel bills.
- Campaign for Assembly, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Election results.
- Campaign for Assembly, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Press clippings; campaign literature; voting tally.
- Campaign for Assembly, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Press clippings; campaign literature; election data.
- Inauguration, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Schedule; invitation to Inauguration.
- Editorial, "The Yonkers Record", 1938 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  "A Pleasant Surprise," October 30, 1938.
- Campaign for Assembly, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  Campaign literature, palm cards, buttons.
- Republican National Convention, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  Malcolm Wilson schedules and expenses.
- Politics, 1939-1958 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  Press clippings on unemployment hearings, 1941; detailed biography; NAR statement (June 30, 1958) on governorship; draft of Malcolm Wilson speech critical of Harriman; 1958 Republican platform.
- Republican State Convention, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  Wilson's renomination acceptance speech.
- Republican State Committee, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  Wilson's renomination acceptance speech; 1970 platform.
- Nelson Rockefeller, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  Campaign for gubernatorial nomination; Wilson correspondence to various supporters; press clippings.
- Gubernatorial Campaign, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  Speeches; miscellaneous campaign material; correspondence; summaries of press articles on campaign.
- Gubernatorial Campaign, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  Miscellaneous correspondence; Young Republican convention reception.
- Gubernatorial Campaign, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  Wilson personal folder; Rockland County information; delegate counts.
- Rockefeller for Governor Clubs, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  Organizing manual; county committees lists; campaign buttons; poster.
- Nelson A. Rockefeller, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  Wilson expense statements on NAR upstate trips reimbursed by Westchester County Republican Committee; miscellaneous correspondence; press clippings.
- Malcolm Wilson Campaigns, 1938-1972 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  Miscellaneous campaign materials.
- City of Yonkers, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  Memos on fiscal plight of Yonkers.
- Yonkers "Exclusion" Bill, 1972-73 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  Materials relating to state legislation permitting City of Yonkers to exceed its constitutional taxing limit by excluding from the amount it levies as taxes the amounts it pays for employee retirement and social security benefits.
- Yonkers "Exclusion" Bill, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  Correspondence; press clippings; exclusion based upon amount needed to finance new pay contracts for city employees.
- Yonkers Bond Bill, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  Bill to allow Yonkers to issue bonds to liquidate an estimated $11.8 million of deficits of prior years; Malcolm Wilson memo to Robert Douglass in support of Governor's signing bill.
- Boyce Thompson Institute, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  Correspondence on relocation of Boyce Thompson Institute for plant research from Yonkers to College of Agriculture at Cornell University.
- Permanent Commission on Public Employees Pension & Retirement Systems Reports of Commission, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Public Employee Pension and Retirement Systems, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  Correspondence; press clippings.
- Retirement Plans, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  Reports: 1) Possible Benefit Formulas of a New Retirement Plan, corrected copy July 24, 1972; 2) Death Benefits Under the Retirement Systems, September 27, 1972.
- Retirement Plans, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  Reports: 1) Occupational Slotting in an All-Inclusive Plan, December 12, 1972; 2) Disability Benefits and the Retirement Systems, November 8, 1972.
- New York City Pensions, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  Reports: 1) State Comptroller's Audit Report on Survey of Various Fringe Benefit Plans, 1973; 2) New York City Pensions, 1973
- Analysis of Recommendations of the New York State Permanent Commission on Public Employee Pension and Retirement Systems: Their Impact on the Public Service, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 35)
- Condon-Wadlin Bill: Taylor Law, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  [Condon-Wadlin Law, 1947, prohibited strikes by public employees]; Legislative research memo on Condon-Wadlin Law; memo on February 6, 1967, meeting at 55th Street; NAR press release February 28, 1967, on bill to replace Condon-Wadlin Law with modified Taylor Law.
- National Conference of Lieutenant Governors, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  Wilson resolution: "Modernizing the Present Twelve-Year Pattern of Primary Education."
- Constitutional Convention, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  Wilson memo from January 23 on three-way telephone conversation between Wilson, NAR, and Anthony Travia (Speaker of the Assembly and convention president) on the convention; Convention Roll Call, September 26; memo by Robert Douglass from September 29 with summary of proposed Constitution; NAR press releases; text of Constitution.
- Regents Scholarships, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  Wilson's letter to the editor of the "New York Times," responding to "Times" editorial urging renewal of in-state use of scholarship money.
- Opening Day of Legislature, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  Wilson's remarks.
- Youth Court Act (Malcolm Wilson personal file), 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  Speech by Malcolm Wilson August 26, 1957; report December 7, 1957 on Youth Court Act by County Judges Association; letter January 15, 1958 to Malcolm Wilson from Judge Samuel Liebowitz supporting repeal of YCA; Malcolm Wilson letters January 23, 1958 to newspaper editors thanking them for support of efforts to repeal YCA.
- Legislative Library, 1971-1973 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  Correspondence on appointment of Librarian.
- Ethics, 1955-1971 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  Resolution creating Special Committee on Ethics and Guidance, March 20, 1954; Report of Committee, 1955, 1956, 1957; Speech by President and Rector James McGinley of Canisius, "Ethics in the Law Enforcement Profession," June 27, 1961; Speech by James Farley, "A War for the Minds of Men," June 4, 1961; Memo to Executive Chamber Staff, August 20, 1963, summarizing editorial comment on legislative ethics; Wilson letter to Robert Moses on World's Fair; WCBS editorial on November 7, 1963 calling for "rigid ethics code" in New York State Legislature; Ethics editorials, 1964; Senate Bill 4594 (March 18, 1964) to establish Code of Ethics; Report (and legislative proposals) of the Special (Legislative) Committee on Ethics, March 6, 1964; miscellaneous memos on ethics; Malcolm Wilson letter to NAR (April 18, 1969) on status of work of Special Commission on Ethical Standards in Public Service; Wilson letter to NAR (December 12, 1969) transmitting report and recommendations of Special Commission; Report of Special Commission; Comptroller's Report (February 16, 1971) listing municipalities and school districts that have failed to file a Code of Ethics.
- Abortion, 1967-1976 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  Articles, editorials, news clippings; Wilson memo on abortion (January 25, 1968); Letter from John Davison Rockefeller 3rd to Wilson, January 29, 1968, and response February 2, 1968; letter from John Davison Rockefeller 3rd to Wilson (January 29, 1968) enclosing John D. Rockefeller 3rd's remarks at International Conference on Abortion of the Association for the Study of Abortion, November 18, 1968; Wilson's handwritten notes; sermon by Bishop Wright, Annual Red Mass September 30, 1962; letter to Legislature on March 6, 1969, from Fordham Law Prof. Charles E. Rice; letter to Legislature on March 1969 from Fordham Law Prof. Robert M. Byrn; Report of Joint Legislative Committee on Revision of Abortion Laws, March 10, 1969; Speech: "The Right to Live" by Rev. Robert Gannon, June 24, 1969, to New York State Trial Judges; Legislative memo (January 2, 1970) on "Problems Related to Abortion Law Repeal;" Senate passage March 18, 1970, of Abortion Bill; analysis of vote; miscellaneous correspondence, news articles, etc.
- New York City Legislation, 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  Letter to NAR from Mayor Wagner & "Legislative Fiscal Program 1961-1962;" October 8, 1961, "New York Times" article on Mayor Wagner proposals.
- New York City Legislation, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  Memo (author unknown) from December 12, 1963 on response to Mayor Wagner's annual legislative program; letter to Wagner and NAR from Citizen's Budget Commission; memo to NAR from T. N. Hurd, February 12, 1963 with second draft of response to Mayor; March 24, 1963 press release from Mayor; analysis March 30, 1963, of New York City finances by state budget staff; letter from Mayor Wagner to Assemblyman Preller April 2, 1963, "New York Times" article April 3, 1963 "City vote Plan to Avert Deficit."
- New York City, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  Newspaper article (February 5, 1965) on election of Anthony Travia as Assembly Speaker; reports analyzing New York City budget requests; report on proposed Constitutional amendment to increase New York City tax rate; February 1966 correspondence with Robert Moses--threatening lawsuit if Triborough Bridge and Tunnel salaries reduced; New York city Tax Program for 1966; analyses of taxes; worksheets on New York City Real Estate Tax Bill; Economic Development Council of New York City analysis; Lindsay's Budget Message; Wilson memo for press release; "Fact Paper on New York City Tax Proposals," June 1, 1966; Wilson's handwritten notes; Wilson memo on June 8, 1967, "My concept of the aid to upstate bus companies was acknowledged to be one of the keys to success in the Legislature (of the bond issue on Mass Transportation);" Senate vote on cigarette tax bill (1968).
- New York City Legislation, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  Malcolm Wilson "aide memoire" on agreement with the leaders and the Governor on $54 million in additional education aid to New York City; comparison of executive salaries under Mayors Lindsay and Wagner; correspondence from Mayor Lindsay re "Urbanaid" and revenue sharing; memo March 28, 1968 from Teachers Retirement System on funding accrued liabilities.
- New York City Subway Fare, 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  Memo 12/4/69 Malcolm Wilson to Hugh Morrow on Pete Hamill column on subway fare; press release December 11, 1969 PSC to consider fare increase of 5 cents of Syracuse Transit Corporation (from $.25 to $.30); press release December 29, 1969 of letter by NAR to Mayor Lindsay re fare; "New York Times" article January 2, 1970 on "Transit Strike Averted."
- Public Schools, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  Dec. 26 memo to Wilson from T. N. Hurd on "trend in average class size."
- Legislature, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  Correspondence on bill to establish a Special Housing Part in the Civil Court; correspondence responding to constituents on legislation; news clippings; May 27, 1971 memo by Malcolm Wilson to NAR on "Peril to Bond Issue Stemming From Remainder of New York City Arterial Plan," additional constituent correspondence.
- Legislature, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  Bills on New York City; memo March 16, 1972 with analysis of New York City budget by John R. Garrison, Malcolm Wilson's Program Secretary, with copy of analysis of the same by the Division of the Budget; miscellaneous correspondence and memos.
- New York City "Moral Obligation Bonds", 1970-1973 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  Office of Legislative Research memo November 13, 1970 "Public Authorities-State of New York;" 1971 bills dealing with authorities or creating funds; May 27, 1971 letter to Malcolm Wilson on bonding limits of authorities; Comptroller Levitt's June 23, 1971 letter to Legislature on magnitude of state debt; editorials on state debt; November 19, 1971, Malcolm Wilson draft letter to NAR with recommendation to limit "moral obligations;" news clippings re state bonding practice; correspondence and memo from Bank of New York on its lack of interest in engaging in negotiating underwriting of HFA bonds; "New York Times" article March 14, 1972 on downgrade of New York's bond rating; press release March 15, 1972 from Senate Majority Leader Brydges on appointment of bi-partisan committee to investigate state's bond rating; memos and bills on establishment of New York Municipal Bond Agency; Malcolm Wilson to NAR urging veto of "Municipal Bond Bank" Bill; miscellaneous correspondence and news articles on Municipal Bond Bank.
- New York City Housing Development Corporation, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  Memos from Malcolm Wilson to Michael Whiteman and Robert Douglass on middle income housing and the "fiscal crisis."
- New York City Budget, 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  September 11, 1979, memo from staff to Standing Committee on the City of New York on Welfare Administration Costs in New York City; October 1969 Fiscal Newsletter of New York City; "New York Times" article December 6, 1969, "Rising city Costs Imperil Budget;" Citizens Budget Commission, December 1969 report; December 22, 1969, memo from T. N. Hurd to Wilson comparing state aide to "Big Six" cities; NAR press release January 12, 1970 on need for federal aid to meet fiscal crisis; NAR press release February 4, 1970 on increase in State aid to "Big Six"; memo February 9, 1970 T. N. Hurd to NAR on "Weekly Report;" memo to NAR February 20, 1970 on Off-Track Betting; Daily News article February 22, 1970 on OTB; Wilson letter February 19, 1970 to Theodore Bardy (Assembly Candidate) on state to local governments; memos on state aid; March 12, 1970 news article on Mayor Lindsay as candidate for higher office; memos, reports, correspondence on New York City finances.
- New York City Budget, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  February 3, 1971, memo from R. L. Dunham to Wilson on CUNY; analysis of United Federation of Teachers contract; NAR press release March 2, 1971 on New York City school situation; memo March 6, 1970 to T. N. Hurd on meeting with New York City budget staff, miscellaneous handwritten notes, correspondence; Interim Report March 15, 1971 of Special Senate Committee to Investigate New York City Board of Education; New York City tax package bills; press releases; memo April 26, 1971 from JFF to Wilson with suggestions for New York City; New York City Executive Budget 1971-1972; news clippings, memos on New York City Budget.
- Speech Material - Irish Constituency, 1959-1972 (Box 4, Folder 57)
- Speech Material - Irish Constituency, 1959-1972 (Box 4, Folder 58)
- Speech Material - Irish Constituency, 1959-1972 (Box 4, Folder 59)
- Speech Material - Irish Constituency, 1959-1972 (Box 4, Folder 60)
- Speech Material - Irish Constituency, 1959-1972 (Box 4, Folder 61)
- Speech Material - German Constituency, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 62)
- Speech Material - Greek Constituency, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 63)
- Speech Material - Italian Constituency, 1959-1972 (Box 4, Folder 64)
- Speech Material - Jewish Constituency, 1959-1972 (Box 4, Folder 65)
- Speech Material - Polish Constituency, 1960, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 66)
- Speech Material - Scottish Constituency, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 67)
- Speech Material - Graduations, 1959-1965 (Box 4, Folder 68)
- Speech Material - Graduations, 1965-1973 (Box 4, Folder 69)
- Speech Material - Education, 1960-1972 (Box 4, Folder 70)
- Speech Material - Environment, 1970-1973 (Box 4, Folder 71)
- Speech Material - Fiscal and Economic, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 72)
- Speech Material - Free Press, 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 73)
- Speech Material - Government Theory, 1965-1972 (Box 4, Folder 74)
- Speech Material - Godkin Lectures, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 75)
- Speech Material - Health, 1967, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 76)
- Speech Material - History, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 77)
- Speech Material - Introductions, jokes and quotes, 1959-1973 (Box 4, Folder 78)
- Speech Material - Labor, 1962-1972 (Box 4, Folder 79)
- Speech Material - Law and Order, 1955-1972 (Box 5, Folder 79A)
- Speech Material - Legislative Annual, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 80)
- Speech Material - Legislative Correspondents Association Dinner, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 81)
- Speech Material - Legislative Correspondents Association Dinner, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 82)
- Speech Material - Legislative Correspondents Association Dinner, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 83)
- Speech Material - Levitt, Arthur speeches, 1967-1972 (Box 5, Folder 84)
- Speech Material - Liberals, Intellectuals and Radicals, 1967-1970 (Box 5, Folder 85)
- Speech Material - Libraries, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 86)
- Speech Material - Lincoln Day, 1957-1967 (Box 5, Folder 87)
- Speech Material - Moses, Robert, 1964-1973 (Box 5, Folder 88)
- Speech Material - Off-Track Betting, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 89)
- Speech Material - Political Ideas, 1939-1973 (Box 5, Folder 90)
- Speech Material - Private Enterprise, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 91)
- Speech Material - Smith, Alfred (Gov.), 1919-1972 (Box 5, Folder 92)
- Speech Material - Miscellaneous, 1962-1973 (Box 5, Folder 93)
- Speech Material - Personal (Box 5, Folder 94)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted material.
- Speeches - Albany College of Pharmacy Commencement, May 31, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 95)
- Speeches - Alfred University Commencement, June 11, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 96)
- Speeches - American-Irish Historical Society, 1966-1972 (Box 5, Folder 97)
  Specific dates for this Folder are April 30, 1966; May 5, 1967; October 4, 1972.
- Speeches - American Legion Annual Convention, July 27, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 98)
- Speeches - Boy Scouts of America Dawn Patrol, February 5, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 99)
- Speeches - Bronx Real Estate Board (Articles), March 1967, March 1972 (Box 5, Folder 100)
- Speeches - Brooklyn Law School Commencement, June 19, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 101)
- Speeches - Canisius College Commencement, June 9, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 102)
- Speeches - Cardinal Newman Library Association, May 24, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 103)
- Speeches - Cardinal Spellman High School Dedication, May 27, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 104)
- Speeches - Cardinal Spellman Youth Center Dedication, May 27, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 105)
- Speeches - Cathedral College of the Immaculate Conception Dedication, December 8, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 106)
- Speeches - Catholic Actors' Guild Communion Breakfast, May 27, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 107)
- Speeches - Catholic Charities Communion Breakfast, March 20, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 108)
- Speeches - Catholic Lawyers Guild Red Mass Breakfast, September 28, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 109)